Guide to the University Historical Material records, 1821-2012 RG0031
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
University historical materials collection
1821-2012
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0031
95.5 Linear Feet
This collection include photos, diplomas, invitations, newspapers, early land holdings, 19th century newspaper accounts of the early college, Civil War records, and memorabilia.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from campus offices and gifts from donors.
Historical Note
This collection was created in January 2005 as a way of bringing together a number of small accessions that had never been assigned to a specific record group in The George Washington University Archives. Some of these accessions represent excellent documentation of the early years of the University, both in written and visual form. These include early land holdings, 19th century newspaper accounts of the early college, Civil War records copied form the National Archives, as well as the first student newpapers. Many are surmised to have come from the office of University Historian Elmer Louis Kayser, who was associated with the University as a student and faculty member from 1914-85.
In 2016 and 2017, with the reprocessing of the Office of the President records, some series of photographs and memorabilia were moved into RG0031, and some series and boxes of records from the office of the president were moved into RG0002, resulting in the current series numbering.
Also in 2017, a significant number of artifacts of minimal research value were deaccessioned.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include student records, blueprints, audio tapes, cassette tapes, invitations, speeches, diplomas, newspapers, photographs and negatives, plat maps, academic costumes, scrapbooks, artifacts, charters, and awards. They date from 1821-2012. They were transferred to the University Archives through various campus offices and individuals. Note that not all series have been fully processed. Please contact staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized in 28 series, numbered 1-7 (two series are numbered 2 and two are numbered 6), 9-20, 24, 25, 31, 33, 34, 37, and 53. Photographs are located in series 1, 2, 33, and 34. Early college records are located in series 3. Audio and video recordings are located in series 4 and 20. The remaining series contain former veritcal files, memorabilia, artifacts, newspapers, scrapbooks, awards, and other miscellanea.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scrapbooks; Washington (D.C.); Videotapes; Audiotapes; Events; Student organizations; Building construction; World War, 1939-1945; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.); Maps; Students; Buildings; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Degrees, Academic; Faculty; Sports; Greek letter societies; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Photographs; Carroll, Thomas Henry; Trachtenberg, Stephen Joel; Colclough, Oswald S.; Bloedorn, W. A. (Walter Andrew); George Washington University. Medical Center; Borden, William Cline; George Washington University; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; George Washington University. Law School; George Washington University--History; Eban, Abba Solomon; Cronkite, Walter; Columbian University; Columbian College in the District of Columbia; Scottish Rite (Masonic order); Samson, G. W. (George Whitefield); Luther Rice; Elliott, Lloyd H.; Mubarak, Muhammad Husni; Morris, Edward Karrick (E.K.); Marvin, Dorothy Betts; Marvin, Cloyd Heck; Levitan, Sar
- Images and visual works, 1859-1990; RG0031 Series 1; 21 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 34, Flat box 37, Box 42, Box 86, Box 95, Box 205, Box 206, Box 265, Box 267, Box 268, Box 269, Box 270, Box 271, Box 87, Flat box 89, Flat box 90, Box 91, Box 92, Box 93, Folder 1, Box 94, Box 262, Box 243, Box 240)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains photographs and negatives of individuals, localities, objects, buildings, events, groups associated with the history of The George Washington University. Most are described at the item level but one set of negatives, grouped at the end of the series, is entered at the box level with item-level content information available in a note field. This series also contains paintings, sculptures, drawings, postcards, and other related artwork and images. The material dates from 1859 through the 1990s.
  - Lisner Hall, 1935 ca. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Text with photograph: "2023 G St., N.W. (Lisner Hall, 1912-1938.) House on left occupied by Easby family. Henry Adams occupied rooms in house on right, 1869-1870. ca. 1935" Includes buildings on either side of Lisner Hall, which occupied this spot from 1912-38, when the building was razed and Lisner Library was constructed. Formerly photgraph #PA-1
  - Quigley's Pharmacy, 1912 ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Formerly photograph #PA-2 SE corner of building.
  - James Monroe Hall, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Text on photograph: "James Monroe Hall, G Street, west of 21st Street 1956." Formerly photograph #PA-3
  - James Monroe Hall, 1968 ca. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Formerly photograph #PA-4 James Monroe Hall, NW Corner, G Street at 21st Street.
  - Medical Department of the Columbian University, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Text on Photograph: "Corcoran building, used from 1867-1902" Text with photograph: "Medical Dept. Building, No. Side of H St., Between 13th & 14th. 1887-1902. Formerly photograph # PA-5 "In 1868, the [Columbian University] Board authorized the enlargement of the building used from 1866-1868 as the Medical School. This involved the addition of a floor and other new construction. In this modified form the building was used until 1902." [Bricks without Straws: The Evolution of George Washington University, Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Professor Cleveland Abbe, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Text on photograph: "Prof Cleveland Abbe" Text with photograph: "Professor Cleveland Abbe, Prof. of Meterology, 1884/5-198/09." Formerly photograph #PA-6
  - First H Street Hospital, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Text on photograph: "Old Prep School, later used as as Hospital" Text with photograph: "1st H St. Hospital. (Originally built in 1882 for Preparatory School (Later called Columbian Academy). When Academy closed, it was remodeled and opened in 1898." Formerly photograph #PA-7
  - H Street Hospital Buildings, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Text on photograph: "1st Prep. School, later used as Hospital." Text with photograph: "H St. Hospital buildings: To left, 1st Hospital on H St., (Originally built for preparatory school, and at center adjoining building constructed in 1902)." Formerly photograph #PA-8
  - Major Murray D. Backhaus, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Text on photograph: "Major Murray D. Backhaus." Formerly photograph #PA-9
  - Colonel John Barner, 1966 ca. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Text on photograph: "Col. John H. Barner [U.S. Army]." Formerly photograph #PA-10.
  - Medical School, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Text on photograph: "Medical School, North side of H St. between 13th + 14th Streets. Three buildings are shown, a fourth is a four story research laboratory (1931) of the building shown (left to right): The first was originally built (1883) as the home of the Prep. School; second is the Univ. Hospital (1902); third, the Medical School, was built on the site of its predecessor (1902). During the period 1887-1921, The Dental School shared the quarters of the Medical School." Formerly photograph #PA-11
  - Medical School, Hall A, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Text on photograph: "Medical School - Hall A." Formerly photograph #PA-12
  - Dean William Allen Wilbur, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Text on photograph: "Dean Wilbur" Formerly photograph #PA-13. Professor of English 1895-1935. Served also as Dean of Columbian College and as University Provost. [George Washington Bulletins 1895-1935]
  - Columbian University Class of 1890 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Text on photograph: "Columbia College Class of 1890. Presented Feb 25, 1935 by Mr. A.P. Tallmadge(?)." Formerly photograph #PA-14. Mabel Nelson Thurston is first on the right, second row. The "original thirteen" female undergraduate students first admitted into the Columbian University. [Bricks without Straw - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Walter G. Ross Hall, 04/1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Text on photograph: "Photo by Kristi Brown. Med. P.R 4/73 New Medical School Ross Hall 23rd St., H+I Sts. 1974." Formerly photograph #PA-15
  - Walter G. Ross Hall and Himmelfarb Health Science Library, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Text on photograph: "Ross Hall (Medical School), 23rd St., H & I Sts." [Multiple copies of photograph with this text appears but not on the one kept] Formerly photograph #PA-16
  - Medical School Library, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Text on photograph: "Med. Sch. Library 1974" Formerly photograph #PA17
  - University Yard, Commencement Ceremony, 1960 ca. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Formerly photograph #PA-18. Believed to be a spring commencement ceremony in University Yard, 1960s. The buildings to the left were removed when the Jacob Burns Law Library was constructed then finished in 1967.
  - G Street at 21st NW, 1960 ca. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Formerly photograph #PA-19
  - Washington Infirmary, 1846 ca. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Text on photograph: "Circular of the Medical Department of the Columbian College, Washington, D.C. 1846" Formerly photograph #PA-20 "The Washington Infirmary. The use of this structure in Judiciary Square, originally the jail but reconstructed as an insane asylum, was granted to the Medical faculty by Congressional action on June 15, 1844, 'for purposes of an infirmary, for medical instruction, and scientific purposes.' In this form it was used until 1852..." [A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Kayser]
  - Lintel Post of Medical School, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Formerly photograph #PA-21 "Two years after the Hospital and Medical School on the site of the original Corcoran building were completed, the name of the University was changed. The monogram CU on the lintel posts of the stairs remained a constant reminder until 1973 - as long as the buliding was occupied - that George Washington University had once been Columbian Unversity" [A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Luis Kayser]
  - University Clinic exterior, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Text on photograph: "University Clinic - exterior of 13-story medical facility at 22nd and Pennsylvania Avenues. Medical Public Relations. George Washington University" Formerly photograph #PA-22. Later known as Medical Faculty Associates.
  - Demolition of old Medical School, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Formerly photograph #PA-23 H Street between 13th and 14th Streets
  - Demolition of old Medical School, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Formerly photograph #PA-24 H Street between 13th and 14th Streets
  - Demolition of old Medical School, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Formerly photograph #PA-25 H Street between 13th and 14th Streets
  - Demolition of old Medical School, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Formerly photograph #PA-26 H Street between 13th and 14th Streets
  - Demolition of old Medical School, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Formerly photograph #PA-27 H Street between 13th and 14th Street
  - National College of Pharmacy, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Text on photograph: "808 Eye [ I ] Street, 1906-1919" Formerly photograph #PA-28
  - Meyer Pavillion, 1965 ca. (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Text on photograph: "Meyer Pavilion #70" Formerly photograph #PA-29. "The Eugene Meyer Pavilion was dedicated on January 21, 1966 ...[including the presence of]...Mrs. Meyer, Speaker John MCCormack, President Elliot, and Dean Parks. The total cost of the Pavilion and of the air conditioning and remodeling of the Hospital was about $7.5 million" [A Medical Center: The Institution Development of Medical Education in George Washington- Elmer Louis Kayser] 22nd Street NW between I and Pennsylvania Avenue
  - University Clinic, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Text on photograph: "University Clinic #72" Formerly photograph #PA-30
  - University Clinic entrance, 1970 ca. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Text on photograph: "Clinic Entrance - 22nd and Penna." Formerly photograph: #PA-31 ["This 13-story building [H.B. Burns Memorial Building] on the southeast corner of Pennsylvania Avenue and 22nd Street was opend on March 20, 1969. [It housed] the University Hospital Clinic....contain[ing] offices, special procedure rooms and laboratories as well as areas for teaching the clinical sciences." - A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Columbian Building, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Text on photograph: "Columbian Bldg., 416 5th St., NW (1969)." Formerly photograph #PA-32
  - Columbian Building, 04/1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Text on photograph: "Columbian Bldg., 416 5th St., NW (1969)." Formerly photograph #PA-33.
  - Columbian Building, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Text on photograph: "Columbian Bldg., 416 St., NW (1969)" Formerly photograph #PA-34
  - Taxonomy Laboratory, 11/06/1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Text on photograph: "General Lab G.W. W. Nov 6 1934" Formerly photograph #PA-35
  - Taxonomy Laboratory, 11/06/1934 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Text on photograph: "Taxonomy Lab G.W.W. Nov 6 1934" Formerly photograph #PA-36
  - Major Jerome Barnes, 1960 ca. (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Text on photograph: "Barnes, Jerome R. Major" Formerly photograph #PA-37
  - Major Jerome Barnes, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Text on photograph: "Barnes, Jerome R" Stamped onto photograph: "Please Return To: Office of Public Relations The George Washington University 1750 Pennsylvania Avenue, N. W. Suite 1207 Washington D.C. 20006 676-6460" [name pin on man being pinned reads Baker]
  - Dean Henry E. Kalusowski, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Formerly photograph # PA-39 ["Henry E. Kalusowski, M.D., Phar. D., Dean of the College of Pharmacy" from A Medical Center: The Insitutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University-Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Dean David Eastburn Buckingham, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Text on photograph: "Buckingham" ["David Eastburn Buckingham, D.V.M., Dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Earl Baldwin McKinley, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Text on photograph: "McKinely" ["Earl Baldwin McKinley, M.D., Dean of the School of Medicine 1931-1938" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser] Formerly photograph # PA-41
  - Dr. William Cline Borden, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Text on photograph: "Borden" Formerly photograph #PA-42 ["Dr. William Cline Borden, M.D., Dean of the Medical School 1909-1931" from A Medical Center: The Institutional development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Dr. John Lewis Parks, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Text on photograph: "John Parks" Formerly photograph #PA-43 ["John L. Parks, M.D., Dean of the School of Medicine 1957-1972, Vice President for Medical Affairs 1972" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Logo for George Washington University, 1971 ca. (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Formerly photograph #PA-44
  - Dean Walter Andrew Bloedorn, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Text on photograph: " Walter Bloedorn MD From 1949 Speculum GWU School of Medicine Yearbook" Formerly photograph #PA-45 ["Walter Andrew Bloedorn, M.D., Dean of School of Medicine, 1938-1957" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser] [text on photo does not appear on this copy of the photograph]
  - Medical School Classroom, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Text on photograph: "Hall A" Formerly photograph # PA-46 ["Medical School on H Street, Hall A"- A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Medical School library, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Text on photograph: "Library" Formerly photograph #PA-47 [Faculty Reading Room] ["Medical School on H Street, Library" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Gross anatomy lab, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Text on photograph: "Anatomy Gross Lab 5th floor" Formerly photograph #PA-48 ["Medical School on H Street" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser].
  - Biochemistry lab, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Text on photograph: "Biochemistry Lab" Formerly photograph # PA-49 ["Medical School on H Street, Laboratories" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Pathology laboratory, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Text on photograph: " Pathology Lab" Formerly photograph # PA-50 [" Medical School Street on H Street, Laboratories" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Anatomy lab, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Text on photograph: "Anatomy Lab" Formerly photograph #PA-51 [Medical School on H Street, Laboratories from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Mother Mathilde Inchelin, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    Formerly photograph #PA-63 ["Mother Mathilde Inchelin, Superioress General of the world-wide Daughters of Charity." "During the greater part of its history, nursing care in the [Washington] Infirmary was given by the Sisters of Charity...Just before the destruction of the building and after the American Sisters of Charity had joined the original foundation of St. Vincent de Paul in Paris, the more familiar habit was worn." from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Daniel Kerfoot Shute, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
    Formerly photograph #PA-65 ["Daniel Kerfoot Shute, M.D., Professor of Anatomy, 1887-1888; Dean, 1894-1897" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Formal designation of University Hospital, 1917 ca. (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Formerly photograph #PA-101 ["Designation of University Hospital on H Street as General Hospital 75, World War 1" from A Medical Center: The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University - Elmer Louis Kayser]
  - Operating room of old University Hospital, 1920 ca. (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Formerly photograph #PA-112 [Comments entered into file - Daniel Borden films the operation (part of title). !!Very good; see Acc#414, Winter 1970, p.9!!]
  - H Street hospital buildings, 1874 ca. (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Text on photograph: "Medical School, north side of H St. between 13th [and] 14th Streets. Three bldgs. are shown, a 4th is a four-story research laboratory (1931) of the bldgs shown (left to right): The first was originally built (1883) as the home of the Prep. School; second, the University Hospital (1902), third, the Medical School, built on the site of its predecessor (1902). During the period 1887-1921, the Dental School shared the quarters of the Medical School. Formerly photograph #PA-113
  - Elmer Louis Kayser, 05/1981 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    Text on photograph: "Dean Elmer Louis Kayser May 1981 Photo by Prof Sherwin Greene Dept of O & RP" Formerly photograph #PA-114
  - Elmer Louis Kayser, 1969 ca. (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Text on photograph: "Photo for Dust Jacket - A Medical Center: Geo Wash. Univ" Formerly photograph #PA-115
  - Elmer Louis Kayser in Lisner Auditorium, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Text on photograph: "Elmer Louis Kayser 1957 Lisner Auditorium" Formerly photograph #PA-116
  - Construction site, Hall of Government, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Text on photograph: "Construction scene The George Washington University" Stamp on photograph that reads: "If not filing, please return: Office of Public Relations The George Washington University 2029 G Street, N.W. Washington 6, D.C." Formerly photograph #PA-117 [Construction site of the Hall of Government.]
  - Setting the capstone at Hall of Government, 05/1938 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Text on photograph: "Setting the Capstone School of Government George Washington University May 1938 Photo R [T?] Griggs" Formerly photography #PA-118
  - 2009 G Street, 06/1936 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    Text on photograph: "June 1936 2009 [G?]." Formerly photograph #PA-120
  - Milton Berman, 01/1951 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Text on photograph: "Milton Berman PBK 1951 June, 7393, [stamped] Sappol Studios 608 610 9th St. N.W. Washington, D.C. Next to the Little Theater" Formerly photograph #PA-122
  - Robert S. Berg, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    Text on photograph: "Robert S. Berg [stamped] Please Return To: Office of Public Relations The George Washington University Suite 1207 1750 Pennsylvania Avenue, N.W. Washington, D.C. 20006" Formerly photograph #PA-123 [M.A.]
  - William W. Berg, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
    Text on photograph: "Berg, William W." Formerly photograph #PA-124 [M.A., C.G.S.?]
  - Major James Bennett, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Text on photograph: "Bennett, James B" Formerly photograph # PA-125 [M.S.]
  - Colonel Edgar J. Becker, undated (Box 1, Folder 67)
    Text on photograph: "Becker, Edward J." Formerly photograph # PA-126
  - Paul E. Bell, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
    Formerly photograph # PA-127 [M.S. in International Affairs]
  - Charles E. Hill, 1923 ca. (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Formerly photograph # PA-128 [Professor, Policital Science]
  - Clara Southmayd Ludlow, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Formerly photograph #PA-130 [1852-1924. Ludlow was a graduate student at George Washington University from 1905-1908 while also instructing in "histology and embryology." She received her PhD in February 1908 at the age of 55. She resigned from teaching in April of 1911 for reasons unknown. Her work centered on mosquitos, publishing 20 of 53 papers on this topic. She is noted as a entomological pioneer. She is buried in Arlington National Cemetary- (taken from her biographical notes at Walter Reed Biosystemics Unit, Smithsonian Institution)]
  - Clara Southmayd Ludlow, undated (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Text on photograph: Advertising and printer information for Scott Photographer. Formerly photograph #PA-131 [1852-1924. Ludlow was a graduate student at George Washington University from 1905-1908 while also instructing in "histology and embryology." She received her PhD in February 1908 at the age of 55. She resigned from teaching in April of 1911 for reasons unknown. Her work centered on the taxonomy of mosquitos, publishing 20 of 53 papers on this topic. She is noted as a entomological pioneer. She is buried in Arlington National Cemetery - (taken from her biographical notes at Walter Reed Biosystemics Unit, Smithsonian Institution)]
  - Clara Southmayd Ludlow at work, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)